A Guide to the Lee-Morgan-Pitts Family Papers, 1798-1955
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Lee-Morgan-Pitts Family Papers, 1798-1955
The Library of Virginia
42619
0.90 cu. ft.
Lee-Morgan-Pitts family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Karolyn Cleveland, Cary, North Carolina, 31 March 2006.
Biographical Information
Richard Bland Lee (1761-1827) was a farmer, lawyer, and politician from Fairfax County, Virginia, and the brother of Henry "Light Horse Harry" Lee (1756-1818). He had six children with wife Elizabeth Collins (1768-1858), including son Richard Bland Lee (1797-1875), who became a colonel in the U.S. Army. Brother Henry Lee and his second wife, Anne Hill Carter (1773-1829), were the parents of General Robert E. Lee (1807-1870), who married Mary Randolph Custis (1808-1873) in 1831. The younger Richard Bland Lee married Julia Anna Marion Prosser (d. 1886) in 1826. Nine of their children lived to adulthood, including Julia Eustis Lee (1830-1910); Evelina Prosser Lee (1832-1905), who married Edwin Cecil Morgan (1827-1867) in 1853; and Myra Gaines Lee (1841-1906), who married Charles Napoleon Civalier (d. ca. 1867) in 1864.
Evelina Lee and Edwin Cecil Morgan had six children, four of whom died in infancy. The surviving two were sons Edwin Lee Morgan (1855-1920) and William Prosser Morgan (1861-1913). Edwin Lee Morgan married Mary Van Zandt (1860-1940) in 1893. William Prosser Morgan married Caroline Pattison Bryan (b. 1863) in 1880. They had one daughter, Evelina Lee Morgan (b. 1880), and resided in Alexandria, Virginia. Evelina married J. Herbert Taylor in 1903.
It appears that Caroline Bryan and William Morgan divorced. Caroline stayed in Alexandria, married Henry Pitts (b. 1843) and with him had two children, Henry Garnett Pitts (1890-1965) and George Bryan Pitts (b. 1894). Both sons were called by their middle names. In 1917, Garnett Pitts married Florence Bouton (b. 1891), the daughter of Charles and Alice Bouton, and sister of Ethel Bouton (b. 1888), all of Patterson, New York. The couple initially resided in New York City, but moved to Washington, D.C., at some point. While there, they welcomed son George Bryan Pitts (also referred to by his middle name), born in 1923. By 1928, the young family had moved back to New York City.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1798-1955, of the Lee-Morgan-Pitts family of Fairfax County and Alexandria, Virginia, and New York City. Represented family members begin with Richard Bland Lee (1761-1827), and continue on to the daughter of his great-grandson, William Prosser Morgan (1861-1913), with wife Caroline Pattison Bryan (b. 1863). Also represented are Caroline's children and other family from her second marriage, to Henry S. Pitts (b. 1843). Items include correspondence; Lee and Morgan genealogies; a Morgan family Bible record; a teacher's lengthy account of her 1856 visit to Arlington House and Washington, D.C.; copies of letters written by Richard Bland Lee (1797-1875) while serving in New Mexico and the second Seminole War; photographs; newspaper clippings; and the baby book of George Bryan Pitts (1923- ).
Contents List
- Papers, 1798-1955 (Box 1-2)
  Papers, 1798-1955, of the Lee-Morgan-Pitts family of Fairfax County and Alexandria, Virginia, and New York City. Represented family members begin with Richard Bland Lee (1761-1827), and continue on to the daughter of his great-grandson, William Prosser Morgan (1861-1913), with wife Caroline Pattison Bryan (b. 1863). Also represented are Caroline's children and other family from her second marriage, to Henry S. Pitts (b. 1843). Items include correspondence; Lee and Morgan genealogies; a Morgan family Bible record; copies of letters written by Richard Bland Lee (1797-1875) while serving in New Mexico and the second Seminole War; photographs; newspaper clippings; and the baby book of George Bryan Pitts (1923- ).
  One notable item is a 17-page typed copy of an 1856 letter from Blanche Birard, reporting on her visit with Martha Custis "Markie" Lee (1827-1899) at Arlington House. Birard, a teacher at Pelham Priory in New Rochelle, New York, goes into great detail about her experiences en route to Virginia; impressions of Washington, D.C., landmarks, including the Capitol building (then undergoing renovation and additions) and the White House; the artwork and furnishings at Arlington House; sitting in on proceedings in the Senate, House of Representatives, and Supreme Court; touring Mount Vernon; encounters with various Lee and Custis family members, and their anecdotes about the Washington family; and comparisons of Northern and Southern servants.
  Also of interest are copies of a 1798 written exchange between Richard Bland Lee (1761-1827) and George Washington (1732-1799) on the subject of Lee's offer of military service in the event of a war with France; a history of the military career of Richard Bland Lee (1797-1875); two original letters written by Mary Custis Lee (1808-1873) and two by Virginia Governor Fitzhugh Lee (1835-1905); and an Episcopal marriage service record for the 1917 wedding of H. Garnett Pitts (1890-1965) and Florence Bouton (b. 1891).
  - Richard Bland Lee (1761-1827) correspondence, 1798 (copy) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Richard Bland Lee (1797-1875) correspondence and military service history, 1833, 1871 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Richard Bland Lee (1797-1875) images (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Julia A. M. Prosser Lee photo and pedigree (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blanche Birard letter, 1856 (copy) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robert E. Lee images (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mary Custis Lee (1808-1873) letters, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fitzhugh Lee (1835-1905) letters, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Myra Lee Civalier images (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Edwin Cecil Morgan and Evelina Prosser Lee Morgan papers, 1827-1905 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    Includes Morgan family Bible record.
  - Edwin Lee Morgan and Mary Van Zandt Morgan receipts, letter, 1902-1904, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - William P. Morgan and Caroline P. Bryan marriage certificate, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Evelina Lee Morgan Taylor photos (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Caroline B. Pitts-Evelina L. M. Taylor letters, 1903-1907 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - George Bryan Pitts (b. 1894) papers (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - H. Garnett Pitts and Florence Bouton wedding service, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - H. Garnett Pitts finances and employment, 1922-1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - H. Garnett Pitts and Florence Bouton Pitts images (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - George Bryan Pitts (1923- ) baby book (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ethel Bouton (b. 1888) papers (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lee-Morgan family genealogies (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified images (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  - Unidentified letters (Box 2, Folder 7)